What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
As you know, I like to
put things to the test.
And today we’re going to ask
YOU to do that with your diet,
using the phytochemical index.
Anything with the word "chemical"
in it may sound a little fishy,
but phytochemicals can
be good for you.
Here's the first story.
How do you rate the
quality of people's diets?
Well, what could be more nutrient
dense than a vegetarian diet?
Indeed, if you compare the quality
of vegetarian diets compared to
nonvegetarian diets, the more
plant-based diets do tend to win out,
and the higher diet quality
in vegetarian diets may in fact
help explain better improvements
in health outcomes.
However, vegetarians appeared
to have higher refined-grain intake,
eating more foods like
white rice and white bread
that have been stripped
of much of their nutrition.
So just because you're
eating a vegetarian diet
doesn't mean you're necessarily
eating optimally healthy.
Those familiar with the science
know the primary health importance
of eating whole plant foods.
So how about a scoring system that
just adds up how many cups of fruit,
vegetables, whole grains, and beans,
split peas, chickpeas and lentils,
and how many ounces of nuts
and seeds per thousand calories,
with or without
counting white potatoes.
Well, just looking at the total intake
of whole plant foods doesn't mean
you're not also stuffing
doughnuts into your face.
So, you could imagine
proportional intake measures,
based on calories or weight
to determine the proportion of
your diet that's whole plant foods.
In that case, you'd get docked
points if you eat things like
animal-derived foods —
meat, dairy, or eggs —
or added sugars and fats.
My favorite proportional intake measure
is McCarty's Phytochemical Index.
I love it because its sheer simplicity,
defined as the percent of dietary
calories derived from foods
rich in phytochemicals.
So, it's a score from 0 to 100:
the percentage of your calories
that are derived from foods
rich in phytochemicals, which
are biologically active substances
naturally found in plants
that may be contributing
to many of the health benefits obtained
from eating whole plant foods.
I mean, monitoring phytochemical
intake in the clinical setting
could have great utility in
assisting people with optimizing
their dietary intake for optimal
health and disease prevention.
However, the quantification
of phytochemicals in foods
or tissue samples is impractical,
expensive, laborious; but hey,
this concept of a phytochemical index
score could be an alternative,
simple method of monitoring
phytochemical intake.
Theoretically, a whole food,
plant-based or vegan diet
that excluded refined grains,
white potatoes, hard liquors,
and added sugars and oils could
achieve a perfect score of 100,
whereas, sadly, the most current
American diets might be lucky to hit 20.
Let's see what's going on. In 1998,
our shopping baskets were filled
with about 20% whole plant foods, and
more recently that has actually shrunk.
Wouldn't it be interesting if researchers
used this index to try to correlate it
with health outcomes?
That's exactly what they did.
Look, we know that studies have
demonstrated vegetarian diets
have a protective association
with weight and body mass index;
five dozen studies have shown
that vegetarians had significantly
lower weight and BMI
compared with non-vegetarians.
And even more studies show that
high intakes of fruits, vegetables,
whole grains and beans
may be protective,
regardless of meat consumption.
So researchers wanted to use an index
that gave points for whole plant foods.
They used a phytochemical index
and tracked people's weight
over the next few years, which
again, I profiled in my video,
"Calculate Your Healthy Eating Score"
on a scale of 0 to 100, simply
reflecting what percentage
of your diet is
whole plant foods.
And even though the healthiest eating
tier only averaged a score of about 40,
which meant the bulk of their diet
was still made up of processed foods
and animal products, just making
whole plant foods a substantial
portion of the diet may prevent
weight gain and decrease body fat.
So it's not all or nothing.
Any steps we can make to
increase our whole plant food intake
may be beneficial.
A couple more studies
have been performed since,
and they all point in the same
direction: about a third of the odds
of abdominal obesity at
higher healthy plant intake
and significantly lower
odds of high triglycerides.
So the index may be a useful
dietary target for weight loss,
where there's less focus on calorie
intake and more on increasing intake
of these high-nutrient,
lower-calorie foods over time.
The latest such study,
published 2020,
suggests the same is
true for childhood obesity.
Even at the same weight,
the same amount of belly fat,
those eating plant-based have
higher insulin sensitivity,
meaning the insulin they make
works better in their body,
perhaps thanks to the compounds
in plants that alleviate inflammation
and quench free radicals.
And indeed, things seemed to improve
as people ate more and more plants.
No wonder researchers found
91% lower odds of prediabetes
for people getting more than half their
calories from healthy plant foods,
significantly lower odds of metabolic
syndrome and high blood pressure,
only about half the odds of being
diagnosed with hypertension
over a 3-year period among
those eating more plants.
Even mental health was impacted.
About 80% less depression,
2/3 less anxiety, 70% less
psychological distress.
What about the Dietary Phytochemical
Index and benign breast diseases,
such as fibrocystic diseases,
ductal ectasia, fatty necrosis,
and all sorts of benign tumors?
The same thing was found: 70%
lower odds of those diseases.
OK, but what about breast cancer?
A higher intake of healthy plant
foods was indeed associated
with a lower risk of breast cancer,
even after controlling for
a long list of other factors,
and not just by a little bit.
Eating twice the proportion of plants
compared to the standard American diet
was linked to more than 90%
lower odds of breast cancer.
What evidence do we
have that scoring higher
is actually better?
Let's find out.
A few years ago, a proposal was
published for a healthy eating index,
and I thought it might be interesting to
look at the latest USDA dietary survey
to see how the standard
American diet is doing.
The index is simple;
it’s a score of 0 to 100,
which simply represents the percent
of dietary calories derived from foods
rich in phytochemicals.
Phytochemical is just a more
technical term for phytonutrient,
since nutrient implies essential for life,
whereas phytochemicals are merely
essential for a long, healthy life.
So if 1% of our diet is composed
of phytonutrient-rich food,
our diet gets a score of 1.
If that’s where half of our calories
come from, then we score 50.
And if that’s all we eat,
we can max out at 100; 100%.
How are Jane and Joe Sixpack doing?
Here is the latest data on
the standard American diet:
3% of calories come
from beans and nuts;
3% from fruit;
5% is vegetables;
23% from grain;
17% is added sugars,
like candy and soda
and other junk;
23% comes from added fats—
butter, margarine, oil, shortening;
and 26% of the American diet
is meat, dairy, and eggs.
For the healthy eating index, we only
get to count phytonutrient-rich foods,
since they’re the ones
most associated with
chronic disease prevention,
treatment, and cure.
So, first off, the reason they’re called
phytonutrients is that, by definition,
they are found in plants—derived from
the Greek word “phyton,” for plant.
So, automatically we
start with a score of 74.
Neither lard nor candy are
phytonutrient-rich either,
so taking away the added fats and oils,
we’re down to 34.
But the grain category
is a combination
of both whole grains—
rich in phytonutrients—
and refined grains, which had the
phytonutrients largely removed.
Only 4% of the American diet
is composed of whole grains—
like oats, barley,
whole wheat, brown rice—
and the rest is highly
processed garbage,
like white flour and cornstarch.
Yikes, down to 15!
But it gets worse.
2/3 of our vegetables are white
potatoes, half of which are potato chips.
The average American eats
23 calories of potato chips every day.
But none of the
white potato products count,
since they contain relatively
few phytonutrients.
Similarly, a third of our fruit calories
are low-phytonutrient juices,
and so the typical American diet
rates 12, out of 100.
So on a scale of like 1 to 10,
we get about a 1.
How do you score a perfect 10?
“Theoretically, a vegan diet
that excluded refined grains,
potato products, hard liquors,
and added sugars and oils could have a
[perfect dietary index rating] of 100.
Sadly, the [score] of most current
American diets would be unlikely to be
as high as 20
[yeah we wish it were 20!]
—which means that there [is]
quite ample room for improvement.”
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social media
to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.